The biggest factor in a health insurance policy
or the biggest discussion is
around room rent
because room rent decides
how much claim amount we will get. Earlier, there used to be 100% restriction on
room rent in those policies,
1% room rent or the day before, room
rent and so on or limit was
specified but now in health and
insurance policies,
room rent restriction is hardly there
in any policy. If you visit a hospital,
most of the times it happens that lower
category rooms are not available, so
if there is a room rent restriction
in your policy, then you may have to incur a lot of expenses out of pocket.
In this regard, today we will
see the calculation with an example, if there is a room rent
restriction, then how much bail you may have to pay
versus policies without
other room rent restrictions.
Before starting the video, Cookriders, if
you have
not yet subscribed, do so because there is a
lot of information.  I
would like to introduce myself to you here
for those who are new, my name is Gurleen Kaur Chek.
I am a Certified Financial Planner. I have been
associated with the insurance industry for the last 18 years and every week I
bring videos for you so that your personal
financial life becomes easy and happy
because the tagline of our company is also
Creating a Wealth of Happiness. Let's
move towards the video. Room Rent
Restriction vs No Room Rent
Restriction. So as I talked about
when you take a health insurance policy,
room rent is a big factor there, that is,
when you visit a hospital,
what is the first thing there,
which room category is available? There is
not just one category in the room category, there are many
categories available,
twin sharing basis room. You will see that there is a
single private room, there is a deluxe room, there is a
suite, there are categories above the suite as well,
presidential seated, so there is
no limit, so what happens is that
all your expenses are connected to the room, today we will discuss that.  Let us
understand with an example. First I would
like to tell you that there are many policies in
which there is room rent restriction. It is
written that you are allowed to give single family
or 1%
off on the right room
in the policy. The second category is where there is other room, that is
you can take any room and there is
no restriction, you
can take any category of room except
suite and above. It also happens that you can
take single private single room, deluxe semi deluxe, you
cannot take suite category.
Then there is a third category where you
can take any room where it is written that
other room, there is no restriction,
you can take any type of room
because what happens is when you go to the hospital, the first thing that the
hospital tells you is that the
room is not available, so what should
we do, what will you do in that,
if you are in a single room or there are
restrictions on your room and
they give you a deluxe super deluxe room, then
what will happen, you will have to pay from your pocket.
How much will you have to spend?
Today we are going to talk about how much you will
actually spend if you
go to a higher category room.
This is not an online answer, you will
say it simply, it is simple maths, like for
example, you will say that
I had to get a camera worth Rs 5000 from the hotel, but I took a room worth
Rs 10000, so the difference is only
Rs 5000. For the number of days I will stay in the hospital, I will pay Rs 5000 for the study papers.
Thoughts it is not like that, everything is included in the
proposal, all the expenses are included,
which we will see in the example,
so I am sharing an excel sheet with you
where I did this calculation, where there was a
policy without room rent camping
and a policy with room rent camping, so we will
talk about how much the customer will have to spend from his pocket, here I have taken an
example, I have taken Rs 5
lakh and have added  If there is any hospitalization for 10 days, then it is
in Policy A that is
your room rent with camping, there is 1%
off time for short room rent camping, so if there is a
policy of Five Luck then a room of up to 5000 will be given
and if there is hospitalization of 10 days then there
is eligibility for a room of up to 50000, if
actually we talk about a policy without room
rent camping, then there
is no cabin there, today its entire bill will be
settled, if there are 100 rooms then
₹10000 will be given in full, how is it without any
other payment, you will get a room by paying ₹10000,
so now we are talking about here,
there after paying ₹10000,
your profit is ₹1 lakh as per the room because if you are
hospitalized for 10 days, here it is calculated at the rate of 5000,
₹50000, if that is lower  If he
lived in a category room, what would be his
expenses? When he upgraded,
what would be his expenses? If
we talk about it in detail, then in a lower category room, the cost would be
50000 rupees and the expenses would be ₹500
doctor consultation visit because
proportionally all the expenses increase.
I calculated that the doctor has made one visit
in a car room only twice in a day and there would
be 20 visits of the doctor in the total hospital
duration, then as per 500 rupees per visit, the
consultation cost would be up to ₹10000 at the rate of 20%. In a lower category
room, Narsingh was charged ₹
50000, surgery cost ₹30000, medicine cost
₹50000 and miscellaneous expenses which are non-
medical expenses would also be 50000. So,
if we do this in total,
if he lived in a lower category room,
what would have been his expenses, we would have covered that only once.  Let's
talk, it was going to be
₹240000. Now what did he do, he took a higher
category room, he took a
category room higher than what was allowed. The
actual room cost was ₹1 lakh.
16000 is the doctor consultation cost because
where the doctor is visiting in the lower category room, he is
charging ₹500.
As soon as the room category gets higher, their
visiting charges also increase. So I
calculated that there is a visit of ₹800 for 20 visits, it will be ₹
16000. Similarly, nursing charges also
increase, but in a higher category room,
after that the surgery cost. Yes, this is actual.
Surgery is performed through surgery.
If you have taken a room in a lower category room, then
your surgery cost is less, whereas
in the higher category it is more.
I will share its example with you later. Similarly,
non-medical expenses are also kept with the medicine cost.
We also have miscellaneous expenses.
270000 were also late for this, so if we talk about the difference,
how much is the actual difference, you should see that 1 lakh - 15000 is the
difference of the first, we auto file it, the
difference amount is ₹16000, so what
they were to be paid actually, what
they were to get in the entire claim, so because of that there was
not just a difference of 50000, there was a
difference of 126000, it means not
only the difference of the room should be paid to
them, their overall expenses will be their skills,
if we should calculate the percentage,
what is the percentage, then we
can calculate that by how much percentage
their expenses increased just by taking a higher category
room, so there is a jump of about 48%, where
we are talking about not only the room
expenses,
you have to bear everything overall, so this
jumps by 3250 percent on an average as soon as
you upgrade the room  Yes, so I would
like to show you an example, this was
taken from a hospital itself, the delivery cost is
different in different room categories, now you are
understanding that delivery is a surgery honey,
whether it is a normal surgery or just
Aryan honey, it is a delivery procedure,
but because the room category is taken separately,
its treatment is also different and
its cost will also change, this screenshot is
in front of you, if you take a twin sharing room
then the package is of ₹141000, if you
take a premium category room then it becomes 2 lakh 2000,
now look, the surgery cost is a surgery
procedure itself, but
everything has escalated, this jam that we are talking about,
48-50% is going to cost even more than that, see further
and in the higher category rooms, they have superior
rooms, suite rooms and presidential
suites, so for the treatment there,
five lakh rupees are being charged for the number of days,
state of ₹140000 in which it is a
very high jump, so that is why
We are talking about room rent restrictions, so here there are so many
different types of maternity
packages, but what I am trying to explain to you is that you should
avoid policies with room rent restrictions because it is not just the
room rent, because what happens
after we reach the hospital,
now what happens, now you cannot do anything about it on
time, but when you are renewing the policy
or not, then keep this in
mind that there should not be any room rent restriction,
try to take a policy with other rooms, because
most of the time when you are
entering the hospital, the
hospital says that the room is not available
and eventually you are given a category above single room, so
now the difference in getting a room becomes quite high
and you have to bear that out of pocket, so I
hope you found this video
helpful and got an idea
about how important room rent is for your
health and Shauryas policy, if you found it useful, then
share it with others too so that it
helps them too.  If you have any
questions or want to share some feedback, you
can do that too. If you
want to tell us in the comment section, please tell us on what the next video is made
and before going, a reminder,
if you have not yet subscribed to our channel, do
subscribe so that you get the
right information and the right time. We will meet
soon in the next video. Space Safe
Take Care By, it was like some policy, there is
no simple answer to it, this is not the only answer,
okay.